<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC1034 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1035 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6672 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6672.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3743 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3743.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4034 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4034.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7816 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7816.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-sury-dnsop-cname-plus-dname-01" ipr="trust200902" updates="1034">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="CNAME-PLUS-DNAME">CNAME+DNAME Name Redirection</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <!-- XXX: this should be Ond&#345;ej, Sur&yacute;but 
              the IETF is Unicode-phobic -->
    <author fullname="Ondrej Sury" initials="O." surname="Sury">
      <organization>Internet Systems Consortium</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street/>
	  <country>CZ</country>
	</postal>
        <email>ondrej@isc.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2018"/>
    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Internet</area>

    <workgroup>dnsop</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>DNS</keyword>
    <keyword>DNAME</keyword>
    <keyword>CNAME</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>This document updates RFC1034 to allow coexistence of a CNAME
      Resource Record with a DNAME Resource Record at the same owner node, which
      provides redirection for a sub-tree of the domain name tree in the DNS
      system, in a parent zone.  By allowing this cooexistence, the DNS system will
      have a way how to create a sub-tree redirection  that includes the
      Resource Records owner name.  This would allow parent zones to create full
      domain aliases.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
	<xref target="RFC1034">RFC&nbsp;1034</xref> defines the CNAME
	resource record for cases when there are multiple names for
	single host.  A CNAME resource record identifies its owner
	name as an alias, and specifies the corresponding canonical
	name in the RDATA section of the resource record.  If a CNAME
	resource record is present at a node, no other data SHOULD be
	present; this ensures that the data for a canonical name and
	its aliases cannot be different.  This rule also ensures that
	a cached CNAME can be used without checking with an
	authoritative server for other resource record types.
      </t>
      <t>
	However there are already existing exceptions to this
	rule.  <xref target="RFC4034">RFC&nbsp;4034</xref> defines
	an exception to RRSIG and NSEC records, which MUST exist for the
	same name as a CNAME resource record in a signed zone.
      </t>

      <t>
	<xref target="RFC6672">RFC&nbsp;6672</xref> defines the DNAME
	resource record, which provides redirection for a sub-tree of
	the domain name tree in the DNS system.  That is, all names
	that end with a particular suffix are redirected to another
	part of the DNS.
      </t>

      <t>
	The DNAME RR and the CNAME RR <xref target="RFC1034">RFC&nbsp;1034</xref>
	cause a lookup to (potentially) return data corresponding to a
	domain name different from the queried domain name.  The
	difference between the two resource records is that the CNAME
	RR directs the lookup of data at its owner to another single
	name, a DNAME RR directs lookups for data at descendents of
	its owner's name to corresponding names under a different
	(single) node of the tree.
      </t>

      <section title="Terminology">
	<t>
	  All the basic terms used in this specification are defined
	  in the documents <xref target="RFC1034">RFC&nbsp;1034</xref>,
	  <xref target="RFC1035">RFC&nbsp;1035</xref>, and
	  <xref target="RFC6672">RFC&nbsp;6672</xref>.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
	<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
          "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
          and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
          described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Motivation">
      <t>
	In some languages, some characters have variants, which
	look different or may look very similar but are identical in
	meaning.  For example, Chinese character U+56FD and its
	variant U+570B look different, but are identical in 
	meaning.  If an Internationalized Domain Label or "IDL"
	<xref target="RFC3743">RFC&nbsp;3743</xref> is composed of
	variant characters, we regard this kind of IDL as an IDL
	variant.  If these IDL variants are put into the DNS for
	resolution, they are expected to be identical in DNS
	resolution.  A more comprehensible example is that we expect
	color.example.com to be equivalent to colour.example.com
	in its DNS resolution.  Currently this is something we are
	unable to achieve without copying the data for the owner of
	the domain record (ie. for the color.example.com) and keeping
	it in sync by some external mechanism.  Having both CNAME+DNAME 
	records in the parent zone will remove this need for
	synchronization.  Without this bundling mechanism, current
	mechanisms such as DNAME or CNAME are not adequate to
	solve all the problems with the emergence of internationalized
	domain names.  The internationalized domain names may have
	aliases or equivalent variants.
      </t>
      <t>
	The CNAME+DNAME solution is not limited to internationalized domain
	names.  This bundling could be used by TLD registries to offer
	an additional service for its registrants.  For example, a hosting
	company could create a generic record for its service and with a
	simple CNAME+DNAME bundle, create all needed DNS
	resource records for providing this service.
      </t>
      <t>
	There are already uses of CNAME which violates existing
	DNS standards by replying with CNAME records in the apex of
	the zone.  This proposal would allow these perpetrators to
	comply with the DNS standard again.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="CNAME+DNAME Bundle">
      <t>
	This proposal doesn't change the wire formats of the existing
	CNAME and DNAME records.  It also doesn't change handling of
	the CNAME and DNAME on the resolver side.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Query processing">
      <t>
	Existing rules for a DNAME RR and a CNAME RR are still valid
	with the following exception: The DNAME and CNAME resource records
	MAY co-exist at the same owner name in the parent zone.
      </t>
      <section title="Processing by Authoritative Servers">
	<t>
	  The authoritative server implementations MUST allow a CNAME
	  record when there is a DNAME record for the same name and
	  vice versa.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The authoritative server implementations compliant with this
	  specification SHOULD add an associated DNAME record into an ADDITIONAL
	  (or ANSWER?) section for any non-DNAME query along with the CNAME
	  record that would be normally required.  This would allow recursive
	  DNS server implementations that understand the DNAME record to
	  synthesize the answers for the subtree directly without making
	  additional queries to the respective authoritative DNS servers.
	</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Processing by Recursive Servers">
	<t>
	  Recursive server implementations MUST NOT reject a CNAME
	  record when there is a DNAME record already present in the
	  cache for the same name and vice versa.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Recursive DNS server implementations SHOULD accept the extra DNAME
	  resource record that would be returned along with the CNAME record in
	  the ADDITIONAL (or ANSWER?) section.
	</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->
    
    <section anchor="Implementation" title="Implementation Report">
      <t>
	The author has implemented a change for the BIND 9 authoritative server
	during the IETF 102 Hackathon in Montreal. A domain with CNAME+DNAME
	can be tested at www.cname-plus-dname.rocks.
      </t>
      <t>
	This experiment confirmed that BIND, Unbound and Google Public
	DNS work fine, Knot Resolver has a bug that makes the DNS answer contain
	the DNAME records, but with RCODE=SERVFAIL, and PowerDNS returns
	RCODE=SERVFAIL for any DNAME query.  The other public DNS
	implementations follow the errors of their respective deployed software.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
	If the recursive DNS server looking for records has enabled DNS
	Query Name Minimization (<xref target="RFC7816">RFC&nbsp;7816</xref>),
	the CNAME+DNAME specification might make the resolver send one more
	label than needed from the original DNS Query Name to the nameservers
	authoritative for the CNAME+DNAME records unless the authoritative DNS
	server preemptively returns the DNAME record along with the CNAME resource
	record for the minimized query. The recursive DNS server would have to 
	understand the additional data in the answer and utilize it to synthesize 
	the answer.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no requests of IANA.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml"?-->
      &RFC1034;

      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml"?-->
      &RFC1035;

      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
      &RFC2119;

      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6672.xml"?-->
      &RFC6672;

      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4034.xml"?-->
      &RFC4034;

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3743.xml"?-->
      &RFC3743;
      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7816.xml"?-->
      &RFC7816;
    </references>
    
    <!-- Change Log
      2010-04-15 version 00
      -->
  </back>
</rfc>
